What if a factory could adapt the moment
conditions change?
Manufacturing systems consist of
interconnected machines, resources, and
processes that harmonically transform
raw materials into finished products.
The performances of a manufacturing
system are often pertinent to the rate
of throughputs, the cost of production,
the quality of finished products, the
resilience to disruptions, or the life
cycle sustainability.
But real factories still face
disruptions such as machine failures,
material shortages, labor challenges,
demand variation, and tooling problems.
When a disruption occurs, production
performance can degrade, and the system
may miss target KPI.
New technologies like digital twin have
been increasingly deployed to address
these challenges. A digital twin
provides a digital representation of the
manufacturing system for data streaming,
visualization, simulation, process
control, and optimization. Digital twin
is powerful, but there is still a
challenge in complex manufacturing
systems. The number of possible
configurations and disruption scenarios
can grow rapidly. Traditional redesign
and simulationbased search can become
timeconuming and computationally
expensive. This research presents a new
generative AI framework for on-fly
manufacturing system design under
disruption. The goal is to generate
adaptive system designs that align
production performance with target KPI.
The framework has three main components,
a predictor, a generator, and a critic.
Together, they learn relationships among
machine availability, design decisions,
and KPI outcomes. As the environment of
a manufacturing job shop is dynamically
evolving, plant managers are provided
with this generative AI tool that
generates candidate designs and
implementation costs by taking a
specific set of input variables. When
disruptions occur to machines, material
handling systems, job orders, or raw
materials, plant managers can feed new
input variables to this tool and
generate reconfigurable designs for
evaluation and assessment. Similarly,
when there is no disruption or the
system is restored to conditions before
disruptions, plant managers can also
input a different set of KPI targets or
job order variations to generate
candidate designs for continuous
improvements. In this vision, the
physical factory, digital twin, and
generative AI work together. The factory
provides the real manufacturing
environment. The digital twin provides
simulation intelligence and the
generative AI framework supports
redesign decisions. This work shows how
generative AI can support resilient
manufacturing by helping factories
respond faster to disruptions and
changing performance goals.